Daf is ס"ח, samech chet, sorry about that, okay, this daf is
ס"ח, samech chet, we start from the גמרא Gemara right after the
משנה Mishnah on ס"ז עמוד ב. samech zayin amud bet. Okay, so
the משנה Mishnah had said that there was a debate, excuse me,
that after they brought the עומר, Omer, they would walk out and
the marketplaces would be filled with roasted grain שלא ברצון חכמים shelo
birtzon Chachamim which was not according to the approval of the Sages,
which was what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said and רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda said it was done with the approval of the Sages. So
we are going to take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. The
גמרא's Gemara issue is going to be that whether to prepare this
stuff, you have to be handling all this food, which is not
kosher until the until the עומר's Omer brought. Is there concern that
you would come to eat it if you're handling it during this
time? So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So ולא
גזר v'lo gazar רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda דילמא אתי למיכל מיניה, dilma
ati l'meichal minei, so the גמרא Gemara says again, ס"ז עמוד ב,
samech zayin amud bet, four lines from the bottom, five lines from
the bottom. Is it really true that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is
not concerned that here you are handling all this grain and roasting
it and getting ready to sell it, that you're not going to
come to accidentally eat from it? ורמינהו, u'reminhu, I'll ask you on
this, רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer בודקין אור לארבעה עשר ובארבעה
עשר שחרית ובשעת הביעור. bodkin or l'arba'ah asar u'b'arba'ah asar shacharit u'bish'at
habiur. So here's a question about what happens if somebody forgets to
destroy חמץ chametz ערב פסח. erev Pesach. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says okay, you're supposed to do
the בדיקה bedika and look for חמץ chametz on the night before,
אור לארבעה עשר, or l'arba'ah asar, the night leading into the night
of the 14th. If you forgot, you do it in the morning.
If you forgot then, you could do it at the time when
you destroy חמץ. chametz. But after the time when you destroy חמץ,
chametz, once it's already פסח, Pesach, you should not go or you
know, midday ערב פסח, erev Pesach, you should not go looking for
the חמץ chametz because you go looking for the חמץ, chametz, you'll
come to accidentally to eat it, you'll be handling חמץ. chametz. וחכמים
אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, the Sages say, no, לא בדק lo badak etc.,
if you didn't check then you can check later, and even if
you didn't check ערב פסח, erev Pesach, you can even check on
פסח Pesach itself. So here you see that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says I don't want you handling חמץ, chametz, you might come to
eat from it, and here you say I don't have a problem
if you handling חדש. chadash. So how do you how do you
reconcile this? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבה, amar Rabbah, says
רבה, Rabbah, or some say רבא, Rava, שאני חדש, shani chadash,
חדש chadash is different, top of ס"ח עמוד א, samech chet amud
aleph, הואיל ולא היתרת לו אלא על ידי קיטוף זכור הוא. ho'il
v'lo hitarta lo ela al yedei kituf zachur hu.
Since you only let them pluck it with their hands and not
actually cut it down with a scythe,
therefore it keeps it in their head that this is different and
they're going to remember and they're not going to come to accidentally
eat from it. Now there's a couple points to be made. Number
one is it assumes that the same people that actually cut the
wheat are the ones that are now the ones that are you
know what do you call it grilling it or roasting it, roasting
it later, roasting it to sell, number one, right? And number two
is very often you would imagine that that would be different. You'd
buy your wheat from somebody, then you would go ahead and be
the middleman and you would you know, roast it and sell it.
And number two is as Michael says correctly, it's a day later,
who remembers what I did yesterday? Today it's just wheat, you know,
that I'm going to keep that in my head. So that's a
pretty funny answer. The other thing is and then we'll see to
what degree the גמרא Gemara keeps with that. The other thing to
note and this is the question that came up is why are
you only allowing them to pluck it because although there's a negative
prohibition to eat חדש chadash until the עומר Omer is brought, ולחם
וקלי וכרמל לא תאכלו עד עצם היום הזה, v'lechem v'kali v'karmel lo
tochlu ad etzem hayom hazeh, you cannot eat any grain until this
day until you bring the עומר. Omer. There's also a מצות עשה
mitzvot aseh if you want to call it that or there's a
מצוה mitzvah to not cut any grain prior because it says because
the עומר's Omer defined as ראשית קצירכם, reshit ktzirchem, the first of
your cutting. So it's exactly a little question, would you formulate that
as a positive מצוה mitzvah not to cut? The more precise way
to formulate that is is that you should not be cutting because
then it will impinge on the קרבן korban status as ראשית קצירכם.
reshit ktzirchem. So there's a value, there's an importance not to cut,
not to compromise the עומר Omer status as ראשית קצירכם. reshit ktzirchem.
So the question is when would that cutting be allowed? This was
raised yesterday. Would it be allowed as soon as you cut the
grain for the עומר Omer or would it be allowed only after
the עומר Omer was brought? The simple sense of our גמרא, Gemara,
the גמרא Gemara says that you're only allowed to you know they
were only allowed to what do you call it to pluck the
to pluck the grain with their hand. Well why is that? Why
couldn't they, after they cut the עומר Omer last night, harvest the
grain after that in order so that they would be then ready
to bring it to the market the next day with an actual
scythe? Could it just be there wasn't too much time between the
cutting of the עומר Omer last night and the bringing it if
you wanted to get all this stuff prepared and you wanted actually
start having, you know, start selling the grain? Everybody's eager for the
new grain, you wanted to do it on a large scale, you
maybe had to do the whole thing even prior to the cutting
of the עומר. Omer. But nevertheless it's, oh so you separate it
with your hands so you're not cutting it. Right, the idea of
the hand is like a שינוי shinui or it's not even a
קציר, katzir, it's less than a שינוי, shinui, it's not קציר. katzir.
The עומר Omer is ראשית, reishis, I'm sorry, I meant to explain
that, the עומר Omer. is ראשית קצירכם, reshit ktzirchem, so if you
use it with your hands, you're not doing a קציר katzir and
then that's allowed whenever you want. What? And then you can do
whatever you want? Right. You can do it even way before the
עומר. Omer And then you can prepare it also way before the
עומר Omer, as well? Yes, yeah, for מנחות. Menachot. Right. So the
גמרא Gemara here says that if you wanted to get the grain
prior to the עומר, Omer you could not harvest it. That would
be a problem of ראשית קציר. reishit katzir. You could do it
with your hand then it's not קציר. katzir. The question I'm asking
now is that would you be allowed to harvest it after the
עומר Omer was cut before the עומר Omer was brought? It's a
little unclear in our גמרא Gemara as it's being very laconic. What?
Yeah, would you be allowed to actually harvest it, doing a normal
type of a cutting after the עומר Omer was cut but before
it was brought? In our גמרא Gemara it's a little unclear. The...
it sounds like the answer is no, because it sounds like the
only thing you could have done with the grain prior to the
bringing of the עומר Omer, is to actually cut it with... you
know, pick it with your hands, not harvest it. That being said,
רמב"ם Rambam actually rules that he says you're not allowed to cut
prior to the cutting of the עומר, Omer and basically after the
עומר Omer has been cut, you are allowed to harvest even if
the עומר Omer. has not yet been brought. The כסף משנה Kesef
Mishneh disagrees with this. כסף משנה Kesef Mishneh says no, you can't
even cut prior to the bringing of the עומר. Omer So there
actually is a question whether after the עומר's Omer. been cut, before
it's been brought, are you allowed to cut your own wheat or
not or grain or barley or whatever prior to the bringing of
the עומר. Omer Okay, so let me just repeat that, I think
that maybe that got a little bit lost. For one more time,
there's a prohibition to eat the new grain prior to the עומר
Omer being brought. ולחם וקלי וכרמל לא תאכלו עד עצם היום הזה
עד הביאכם את קרבן אלהיכם, U'lechem v'kali v'karmel lo tochlu ad etzem
hayom hazeh ad haviachem et korban elokeichem, until the עומר Omer is
brought. So prior to the עומר Omer being brought in the middle
of the 16th of ניסן, Nissan, there's a negative prohibition you can't
eat the new grain. There's another issue which is you're not allowed
to harvest the new grain prior to the עומר Omer because the
עומר Omer has to be defined as ראשית קצירכם. reishit katzirchem. It
has to be the first of the cutting, something cannot be cut
prior to that. So the question becomes, well, when would that be
a problem? What if as long as I cut it first, even
if it hasn't been brought, can I still start cutting my other
grain? Because it's still ראשית קצירכם, reishit katzirchem, or no, maybe the
עומר Omer had to be the only thing that was cut at
the moment it was brought, and I'm not allowed to do any
cutting until the עומר Omer. was actually brought. And that's a little
bit unclear. It's debated in the... רמב"ם Rambam says one thing, כסף
משנה Kesef Mishneh argues. Anyway, this גמרא Gemara makes it sound a
little bit that until it was brought, you're not allowed to do
any harvesting. The only thing you can do is pick it with
your hands, and that's not considered harvesting. You know with the תרומות
ומעשרות, trumot u'maasrot, you know there's like certain קולא kula that you
can like snack on it and all that, right? Yeah. So there's
none of that over here, is there? No, in terms of the
prohibition to eat, no, absolutely not. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay, so therefore because you had to pick it with
your hands, you're going to remember you won't come to eat it.
How will people know when it's brought? Is it always supposed to...
So we're going to get to that... so we're going to get
to that in the next משנה. mishna. Okay, the next משנה mishna
will say that they knew that it would be brought by midday.
That's the main point. There was a time that they definitely... maybe
sometimes it would be earlier, but they knew by midday it would
definitely have been brought. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said back, תינח קצירה.
tinach katzira. So that's fine that at the moment of cutting, you're
going to remember and you won't come to pop some in your
mouth because you're not going to be cutting, you're going to be
using your hands. So you'll remember at that moment that you're not
allowed to eat it and you won't pop it in your mouth.
But you know you handle it at a lot of stages after
the cutting: טחינה והרקדה, techina v'herkeda, grinding and sifting. מאי אית למימר?
Mai it leimeimar? What's going to... what can you say? How will
you remember not to accidentally just pop some in your mouth? So
there's not a good explanation for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in general
is concerned you might forget and come to eat something when it's
forbidden, why is he not concerned here? You're not doing anything different
in the grinding and the sifting, why is he not concerned here?
Eat it raw. Apparently. What? Yeah, but not roasted yet. Right, I
understand. So that could have been your answer. You could still ask,
how do you know you won't come to eat it after you've
roasted it before you're actually selling it? So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says, הא לא קשיא, ha
lo kashya, that's not difficult. טחינה בריחיא דידא. Techina bereichaya d'yada. Maybe
we would ask you to do a שינוי shinuy even in the
processing of it. Maybe you should grind it with a hand mill,
not a water mill.
Or הרקדה אגבי נפה, herkeda agabei nafah, on the back of the
sieve, not in the inside of the sieve. So, which is a
funny answer because as opposed to the idea of using your hand
to pick it, there there was a real requirement, you're not allowed
to cut prior to the עומר. omer So by necessity you're using
your hand.
Here, where there's no real requirement to do a שינוי, shinuy, once
you pick it you can grind it and sift it however. So
here we're introducing a new idea, oh, if רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
is not going to be concerned, for him not to be concerned
you might come to eat, maybe we'll force you to do a
שינוי shinuy along the way. But that was never said in the
משנה, mishna, there was never an assumption you were doing a שינוי.
shinuy. The only thing you can assume is that the way it
was harvested was different. He says ברצון חכמים היו עושים. b'ratzon hachachamim
hayu osim. I mean that's even stronger. Okay, so let's take a
look, right. So the גמרא Gemara continues. So the גמרא Gemara says,
one minute, בית השלחין ושאר קצירה, beit hashalachin v'sha'ar katzira,
how about irrigated fields? Irrigated fields is actually not a problem to
harvest. How do you know? דתנן, Detnan, it taught in a later
משנה, mishna, קוצרין בית השלחין שבעמקים. kotzin beit hashalachin sheba'amakim. You're allowed
to harvest, you're allowed to like harvest, that's the right word, right?
For cutting grain, harvest? No? Okay. You're allowed to harvest in the
irrigated fields in the valleys, אבל לא גודשים, aval lo godshim, but
you can't pile it up. Now why are you allowed to harvest?
Because you don't bring the עומר omer from the בית השלחין. Beis
Hashalchin. Why don't you bring an עומר omer from the בית השלחין,
Beis Hashalchin, which is an irrigated field? So basically because it's not
considered to be the ideal grain. Now תוספות Tosfos has a whole
problem which is, okay, it's not ideal, but presumably בדיעבד b'di'eved you're
יוצא. yotzei. So תוספות Tosfos has two explanations. One is even if
it's true that בדיעבד b'di'eved it counts, since this is not the
place where you're supposed to bring the עומר omer. from, it's not
a problem of ראשית קצירכם, reishis ketzirchem, which is an interesting idea
because ראשית קצירכם reishis ketzirchem means that even if it's not the
very first thing cut. In a way, as long as it's the
first thing cut from the grain that could have made its way
to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, as long as this was the
first that was cut from that grain that could have been brought,
that's enough to define it as ראשית, reishis... although if you look
at the entire land of ישראל, Yisrael, it was not the first
thing harvested. It's a very surprising idea. תוספות's Tosfos other answer is,
תוספות Tosfos just has two possibilities. One is because לכתחילה lechatchila you
don't bring from it, it's not a problem of ראשית קצירכם, reishis
ketzirchem, and then he says, well maybe when the גמרא Gemara says
later that בדיעבד b'di'eved it's good from an irrigated field, that's a
סתם stam irrigated field. Here where we say an irrigated field in
the valley, so presumably that's like a doubly bad field. I'm not
enough of a, you know, somebody farmer or somebody who deals with
agriculture to comment on that, but if it's somehow a doubly bad
field, it's both in the valley so it's not the and it's
irrigated, there maybe even בדיעבד b'di'eved you're not יוצא. yotzei. So number
one, it raises an interesting question about is there any grain that
even בדיעבד b'di'eved is not just not choice grain, but even after
the fact would not work for the עומר. omer. If it's in
ישראל, Yisrael, outside of ישראל Yisrael certainly cannot work. That's one class.
But the other surprising point is that it doesn't, you're allowed to
harvest it. It doesn't impact the status of the grain being considered
that's brought as ראשית קצירכם. reishis ketzirchem. Now it makes sense if
you focus the problem the other way. Not that you have to
ensure that what's brought is ראשית קצירכם, reishis ketzirchem, but the other
way, which is you're not allowed to cut anything, anything until you
cut the עומר. omer Sort of like the same way the bringing
of the עומר omer allows it to be eaten, the cutting of
the עומר omer allows the grain to be cut. That's a reframing.
It's not like the problem with cutting is that then the עומר's
omer not ראשית קצירכם. reishis ketzirchem. The idea is the cutting of
the עומר omer. permits the grain to be cut. If you understand
it that way then you can say, well maybe the only stuff
that's prohibited to be cut is stuff that could be brought as
the עומר. omer, Other types of grain, there's no prohibition, and therefore
you do not, it starts off as being permissible. But it is
strange that we are saying that it does not require all grain,
the prohibition doesn't apply to all grain. Yes, מרדכי? Mordechai? You have...
instead of trying to say it's like a bad field, because I
think that's actually the opposite. Irrigated fields and valley fields are more
hydrated. Really? Maybe more hydrated, but what about the quality of the
grain? But let's hear what you've got. I'm wondering if it's because
of the seasonality tie-in of the whole thing. Meaning a non-irrigated field
is dependent on the rains from השם Hashem and has a whole
relationship of ארץ, eretz, that's a very good thing, its proper time
and everything, that the עומר, omer that I have a קרבן korban
relationship to, whereas when it's done by man, I pipe the water
in here, I made the whole thing, the relationship is different from
that grain and it makes it bring it much earlier if I
decide to plant earlier. No, I think that's a great point and
I hadn't had a chance to research it, but I was wondering
the same thing whether is it really based on the idea of
it being choice or somehow the fact if it's not based on
the rains, then it's as you say, it's sort of like it's
not based on nature, it's more man controlled, and therefore the idea
that the עומר omer which is based on the natural cycles doesn't
really relate to it as much. I think that's a great question,
that's a great approach. I haven't sort of researched it enough to
comment on that. תוספות Tosfos certainly assumes that it's based on the
quality. But
what should also be mentioned here as a parenthetical is, you
know, when people are trying to deal with the whole prohibition, well
I'll just say two points. We'll talk about it a little bit
more later today, but the whole prohibition of eating חדש chadash and
does it apply in חוץ לארץ? chutz la'aretz? And if it applies
in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, how do we not, you know, how
come the practice has been for so long not to be concerned
about it? So there have been a couple of answers and some,
I believe it's the ערוך השולחן Aruch Hashulchan tries to say, not
only is the prohibition of cutting limited to the things that you
can bring the עומר omer from, but the prohibition of eating is
also only limited to those things that the עומר omer can come
from. And since you can't bring the עומר omer from grain outside
of ישראל, Yisrael, there's no prohibition to eat. Now the problem is
that the גמרא Gemara never says that, and then you would never
have had an opinion that חדש chadash is אסור assur outside of
ישראל. Yisrael. But that's what he tries to do to somehow justify
the practice, and that's interesting again to notice this strange idea that
the prohibition of cutting only relates to the stuff you can bring
the עומר Omer from, that the prohibition to eat applies to all
grain, not just the stuff. The other though point to be made
in here some people do is why is חדש chadash such a
huge issue outside of ישראל? Yisrael? I mean normally the way the
תורה Torah has the system set up is that at most you
have to wait a few days or a week. I mean this
is ראשית... To the very first of the crops, the barley is
just beginning to ripen. So how much does it hurt people to
say don't jump and eat it until the עומר Omer is brought?
It's a few days at most, right? The problem is what happened
that outside of Israel and in Israel that's still the case, but
outside of Israel especially as you move further away from the equator,
they develop two crops of grain. There was the winter wheat and
the I guess spring wheat. So the winter wheat, which is ready
around gets harvested around I don't know what time, but some time
after ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah time I think or something. So there
you have all six months until you know פסח Pesach is going
to come about and that was not the reality in Israel, but
it was reality outside of Israel. So I think there are those
that try to suggest something similar maybe along what מרדכי זאב Mordechai
Zev says in בית השולחן Beis HaShulchan that maybe the עומר Omer
is only required to מתיר matir the stuff that's going to be
ripened by the time of פסח, Pesach, but the stuff that was
already ripened and harvested or whatever way before פסח, Pesach, now again
these are post-facto you know that maybe you don't need the עומר
Omer? to מתיר. matir. These are very weak approaches that aren't based
on any sources but are attempts to try to justify you know
why outside of Israel people are not so careful about חדש. Chadash.
I'll talk a little bit more about that later. The reason I
bring it up now is it does tie into מרדכי'ס Mordechai's point
which is you know what degree do you say that everything sort
of relates to the עומר? Omer? What if it's an earlier season
of wheat? And I think what you're suggesting about the בית השולחן
Beis HaShulchan is definitely possible. If it's not based on the rain,
then it's not based on the seasons, then to what degree does
it relate to the עומר? Omer But what you have here now
is the following just so that we get the because these are
definitely core ideas about עומר Omer, and I don't want them to
be missed. Remember one is not only can you not eat prior
to the עומר, Omer. you also can't harvest prior to the עומר.
Omer There's a question as I said in the ראשונים Rishonim whether
that means prior to the cutting of the עומר Omer. or the
bringing of the עומר. Omer But here the גמרא Gemara says that
if you wanted to get the wheat before the עומר Omer was
brought, what you would do is you would pick it with your
hand. That's not considered קציר. Katzir.
Conceptually that could be framed as either you have to do that
to ensure that the עומר Omer, is considered ראשית קצירכם Reishit Katzirchem
or to frame it another way, the עומר, Omer the bringing or
the cutting of the עומר Omer permits is a מתיר matir permits
the other cutting. What is interesting is that we see that the
prohibition of cutting the new grain only applied to grain from which
the עומר Omer could be brought and in that way it's different
than the prohibition of eating the new grain which applies to all
of the grain. Okay, so therefore now back to the גמרא'ס Gemara's
point. The גמרא Gemara says so one minute, if you can harvest
grain and there's no prohibition of cutting, there is a prohibition of
eating and the גמרא Gemara here is quite clear about that, there's
no prohibition of cutting prior to the עומר Omer this grain from
the irrigated fields, what's going to make people remember and stop them
from accidentally eating it? So why is רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda not
concerned that you might come to eat it? Again notice the גמרא
Gemara takes for granted that although you're allowed to harvest this grain,
you're not allowed to eat it. So therefore the גמרא'ס Gemara's question
is according to רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda how are people going to
remember and not accidentally eat it if they're handling it before before
the עומר Omer. is brought? So let's take a look at the
answer. So מאי איכא למימר mai ika l'meimar what can you say?
אלא אמר אביי Ella amar Abaye so therefore rather אביי Abaye says
חדש בדיל מיניה חמץ לא בדיל מיניה. Chadash badil minei, chametz lo
badil minei. Now this is a little ironic. We might have said
what are people most likely to sort of see as taboo and
keep a distance from? We would have definitely said חמץ chametz more
than חדש Chadash because we here in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz almost
ignore the prohibition of חדש. Chadash. But he says but if you're
living in Israel and if you're living in a place where חדש
Chadash is a real prohibition, okay, and people treat it as a
real prohibition, I mean it's a real prohibition in חוץ לארץ Chutz
La'aretz too but anyway, so therefore he says so until now you
haven't been touching any of the new grain. Your default not default
your your your current status what's the word I'm looking for here
anyway you know it had been maybe even default anyway had been
not to eat the new grain. So until you're given permission you
know to keep your distance from חדש. Chadash. So even if you're
cutting it and grinding it and getting it ready to sell, in
your mind this is still taboo and forbidden until you get the
signal that it's permitted. So you're not going to accidentally come to
eat it. חמץ, Chametz, although ironically it's going to be פסח Pesach
in a half an hour or you know six hours and you've
spent the last two weeks getting ready for פסח, Pesach, nevertheless you've
still been eating חמץ. chametz. Your default has been to eat חמץ.
chametz. So therefore רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says I'm more concerned you'll
accidentally eat חמץ chametz ערב פסח Erev Pesach than I'm concerned you'll
eat חדש, Chadash, you know the day you know the day before
the bringing of the עומר. Omer, Okay, that makes a lot of
sense. So that's what אביי Abaye says. No, too bad. Okay, why
not? There's a difference, חמץ chametz looks different than non-חמץ. chametz. Right.
This is
all the grain looks the same, even in grain. That's a good
point. They've been eating wheat the whole year. That's a good point.
Old wheat looks the same. That's a very good point. All right.
I don't know what to say. It's a very good point. But
you know I I also don't know in a yeah, it's a
good question what the reality was, how much fresh grain, fresh flour
they had available. You know could be if you only had one
wheat season, right, and you didn't do a lot of importing or
whatever, it could be that you know that most that maybe there
even wasn't well, I guess that's not true but people were baking
מצות matzahs and people are definitely storing the flour. Flour stores very
well. Yeah. Yeah, it's a good point.
That is true. You don't have to hint to me that that
is true, with us that we have a wheat, a winter wheat
and a spring wheat. So the winter wheat has different baking qualities,
different amount of gluten than the spring wheat, and therefore for example
even people that are מקפיד *makpid* on חדש chodash *chodosh* can basically
eat like pizza because, you know, pizza they always use a certain
type, I think it's the spring wheat which doesn't rise as much.
So actually people, you know, there, you know, the normal flour you
get in the supermarket is a blend of the spring and the
winter wheat. But people that are like in the industrial level, in
the business, there is a difference between the spring and the winter
wheat and there are some products that you know they use spring
wheat for, so therefore you know the what is okay. The problem
again outside of Israel is that the winter wheat has six months
on the market before פסח Pesach, *Pesach* comes about. But in Israel
you didn't have that. In Israel you had one wheat season. So
you didn't have, it was just, you know, you did not have
these different qualities. All the flour was spring wheat. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, okay. אמר רבא *Amar Rava*,
so רבא *Rava* says דרבי יהודה *de-Rabbi Yehudah* דרבי יהודה *de-Rabbi Yehudah*
קשיא *kashya*, דרבנן d'rabonon *de-Rabbanan* דרבנן d'rabonon, *de-Rabbanan* לא קשיא *lo kashya*.
One minute, you're only bothered that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehudah*
is contradicting himself, that by חדש chodash. *chodosh* he says it's okay
to handle it and by חמץ *chametz* he says it's not okay?
How about the רבנן *Rabbanan*? They're also contradicting themselves. So how do
you know, I mean he's sort of saying it בתמיה *be-tmiah*, how
can you say the רבנן *Rabbanan* and the רבנן *Rabbanan* are not
a question? אלא אמר רבא *Ella amar Rava*, so rather רבא *Rava*
says here's the full answer: דרבי יהודה *de-Rabbi Yehudah* דרבי יהודה *de-Rabbi
Yehudah* לא קשיא *lo kashya*, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehudah* is not contradicting
himself כדשנינן *kide-shani-nan* like we answered, like אביי *Abaye* said, that רבי
יהודה'ס *Rabbi Yehudah's* okay with you handling, with you handling חדש chodash
*chodosh*, you know it's off limits. He's not okay with you handling
חמץ *chametz* because you have not yet you know started treating it
as forbidden. And that's how that way works. דרבנן *De-Rabbanan* דרבנן *de-Rabbanan*?
How about the רבנן *Rabbanan*? How come they're okay with you handling
חדש chadash *chodosh* and not, excuse me, how come they're not okay
with you handling חדש Chadash *chodosh* and they're okay with you handling
חמץ *chametz*? So here's why the רבנן *Rabbanan* are not contradicting: הוא
עצמו מחזר עליו לשורפו מיכל אכיל ליה *Hu atzmo mechazer alav lesorfo
meichal achil lei*? 'Cause the רבנן *Rabbanan* would say look, in general
I'm concerned that as they're handling this stuff they'll come to eat
from it. And that's why the רבנן *Rabbanan* said that they did
not like the fact that the stores started selling the, you know,
the roasted grain. Who allowed you to start handling this grain before
חדש *chodosh* is permissible? Okay, so they are afraid you will come,
so how come they let you check and destroy חמץ *chametz* on,
for חמץ *chametz* and destroy it even on פסח Pesach. *Pesach* itself?
So they say very clearly, if your whole goal is on a
search and destroy mission, you're looking for the חמץ *chametz* for the
sake of destroying it, you're not going to accidentally pop it in
your mouth. Okay, whereas if you're here, you're handling the חדש *chodosh*
because you're about to start selling it, then you might very well
pop it in your mouth. So that's what the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
says, there's different explanation. The רבנן *Rabbanan* base, you know, it depends
what sort of mindset you're in. If you're looking to destroy the
חמץ *chametz* you won't eat it so we allow you to handle
the חמץ *chametz*. If you're looking to sell the חדש *chodosh* you
might come to eat it we don't. רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehudah* says
it has to do with what your practice has been until now.
Until now חדש *chodosh* has been forbidden so therefore we allow you
to handle the חדש *chodosh*. חמץ *chametz* has been permissible we do
not. I should make a comment that both of these though, you
know, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* never says that there's a problem of
okay handling חלב *cheilev*. Let's, you know,
you're not allowed to somehow handle, you know, טריפה *treifa* and חזיר
*chazir* and נבילה *neveila*, you might come to eat from it. And
the reason is obvious and that goes to the line in the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* about בדילי מיניה *badilei minei*, which is that things
that are not kosher food we know to keep our distance from.
Here this is all grain, right? So there's a time of the
year that חמץ *chametz* is אסור *assur*. There's a time of the
year that חדש *chodosh* is אסור *assur*. So you can argue have
I been בדילי *badilei* חדש *chodosh* until now or not? What's been
my default etc. But at the end of the year, at the
end of the day, there's a good likelihood you're going to see,
you know, psychologically you'll feel it's kosher and you might come to
eat it and we might have to make safeguards. The רבנן *Rabbanan*
did not make any such safeguards when you were dealing with real
טריפה *treifa* objects. Okay, the other related thing has to do with,
for example, בשר וחלב *basar ve-chalav*. Sometimes you have all these safeguards
about don't eat meat and milk on the same table, you might
accidentally come to eat one from the other. And there similarly the
אחרונים *Achronim* explain you don't say don't eat kosher and non-kosher food
at the same table, like if
your non-Jewish employee, colleague is eating non-kosher food you have to be
at a different table? No. But if your Jewish friend is eating
milk and you're eating meat then you have to have a separation.
Why? Because things that are basically kosher but in this context are
a problem, you might forget. And things that are obviously not kosher
you won't. And that's the principle of בדילי מיניה *badilei minei*. Yes,
this חדש *chodosh* also carries a דבר שיש לו מתירין *davar she-yesh
lo matirin*. Yes, חדש *chodosh* also does have that greater problem of
דבר שיש לו מתירין *davar she-yesh lo matirin*. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* wraps this up. רב אשי Rav Ashi אמר *Rav
Ashi amar*, דרבי יהודה *de-Rabbi Yehudah* דרבי יהודה *de-Rabbi Yehudah* לא קשיא
*lo kashya*. Here's how רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehudah* and רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehudah* is not a problem. Why does רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehudah* concerned
about your eating חמץ *chametz* and not concerned about your eating חדש
*chodosh*?
So here's why. קמח קלי תנן *Kemach kali tenan*, that the משנה
Mishna. *Mishnah* says that you can only do roasted grain. So he's
basically saying that the roasted grain is a type of a היכר
*heker* and therefore you know that you, you know, it's special and
you won't accidentally come to eat from it. It's not all grain,
it's only roasted grain. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not having...
So the גמרא Gemara says דהא דרב אשי ברותא היא deha d'Rav
Ashi beruta hi or בדותא היא. beduta hi. That statement of רב
אשי Rav Ashi is a joke or wrong. The גמרא Gemara, it's
a phrase that does not crop up too much in the גמרא,
Gemara ברותא beruta or בדותא, beduta, and usually used in context with
רב אשי Rav Ashi, statements. So go figure, okay, when the גמרא
Gemara really doesn't like poor רב אשי, Rav Ashi doesn't like its
statement, seems like a good approach, it says no that's totally a
joke, that's wrong.
תינח ממקלי ואילך, tenach mi-mikali v'eilach, I understand from the time you
roast it that it's different and you'll remember and won't come to
eat from it. עד קלי מאי איכא למימר, ad kali mai ika
lemeimar, until you roast it what's going to remind you that it's
different and you won't come to eat from it? וכי תימא הכי
נמי על ידי קיטוף, v'ki teima hachi nami al yedei kituf, and
you'll say no there also they'll do a שינוי, shinuy, I'm not
allowed to harvest it, I have to pluck it with my hands,
so every stage there'll be something to remind me. Says the גמרא,
Gemara בית השלחין דשרי למיחצד מאי איכא למימר, Beis Hashalchin desharei limichzad
mai ika lemeimar, like we said before, what about the irrigated fields
that you don't have to do any שינוי shinuy and you're allowed
to harvest them naturally? אלא הא דרב אשי ברותא היא, ela ha
d'Rav Ashi beruta hi, that statement of רב אשי Rav Ashi is
wrong or is a joke and we don't rule like it. So
basically there's a question here, obviously people would be very eager to
get the new grain as soon as the חדש was brought, everybody
would be very eager. How much do we allow the suppliers, you
know, the middlemen to get all that stuff ready? Are we concerned
that in the processing they might come accidentally to eat it? But
again what's interesting for us in addition to that דרבנן concern is
things we're learning about חדש. Number one, it's forbidden to harvest the
new grain
until the עומר, Omer whether it means until the עומר Omer is
cut or until the עומר Omer is brought is somewhat debatable, but
it's at least forbidden to harvest. On the other hand, what's interesting
is although it's permissible to harvest fields from which the grain cannot
be brought, which includes the irrigated fields, I very much like Mordechai's
approach, although it's not the approach of תוספות, Tosafot, but there are
fields that you don't at least לכתחילה l'chatchila don't bring from and
therefore there is no prohibition to harvest, but the grain is still
forbidden to be eaten. Okay, so we are seeing though this new
idea of this prohibition of harvesting. Wasn't it רב אשי the elder?
You
allow yes, except he really wasn't, according to, you know, the גמרא,
Gemara רש"י Rashi or whatever, the גמרא Gemara says רבינא ורב אשי
סוף הוראה, Ravina v'Rav Ashi sof hora'ah, and רש"י Rashi says that
means that they basically edited the גמרא Gemara and they are the
last אמוראים, Amoraim, or almost the last אמוראים Amoraim chronologically that are
mentioned in the גמרא, Gemara but they're still not the sort of
סתם stam editors, the people, the final anonymous editors that really put
it all together at the end. So maybe tell us the story
out, now listen to me, maybe not though,
okay. All right, so now let's take a look at the next
משנה. Mishna:
משקרב העומר הותר חדש מיד, mishakaraf HaOmer hutar chodash miyad, from the
moment the עומר Omer was brought, the new grain became immediately permissible,
from the moment the עומר Omer was brought. הרחוקים מותרים מחצות היום
ולהלן, harichokim mutarim mechatzot hayom u'lehallan, and here you go רבקה, Rivka,
people that were far away from the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash that
did not know when it was brought, from midday on they knew
that they could eat the new grain because they knew it definitely
would have been brought by noon. Okay, so sometimes earlier, but definitely
by noon it would be brought, guaranteed. משחרב בית המקדש, mishecharav Beis
Hamikdash,
once the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash was destroyed, now there's the question,
when does the new grain become permissible once the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash is destroyed? Right, there's no עומר Omer, to make it permissible.
התקין יוחנן בן זכאי שיהא יום הנף כולו אסור, hitkin Yochanan ben
Zakkai she'yehei yom hanaf kulo assur, יוחנן בן זכאי Yochanan ben Zakkai
establishes that the day of waving, it's interesting apparently they gave a
name to the day of the second day of פסח, Pesach they
started, it was called יום הנף, Yom HaNaf, the day of waving
of the עומר, Omer והניפתם את העומר, v'hanifchem es ha'omer, the תורה
Torah certainly highlights the idea that the עומר Omer, is waved, so
that became its name. So that day was completely forbidden, it would
only be permissible on the seventeenth. The implication of this is that
biblically it would be permissible from the beginning of the day if
there's no עומר, Omer from the beginning of the sixteenth, but יוחנן
בן זכאי Yochanan ben Zakkai said, you know, since when there's a
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash it's not permissible at the beginning of the
day, it's only permissible when the עומר Omer, is brought, we're going
to wait till the next day, we're going to wait till the
seventeenth. That's what he was מתקן. metaken. אמר רבי יהודה amar Rabbi
Yehuda and רבי יהודה said, it's not a דרבנן, it's a דאורייתא,
d'oraisa, והלא מן התורה הוא אסור, v'halo min HaTorah hu assur, it's
biblically forbidden the whole day if there's no עומר, Omer שנאמר עד
עצם היום הזה, shene'emar ad etzem hayom hazeh, until the essence of
this day, which he understands means until the entire day passes, until
this day is complete, it's forbidden unless you bring the עומר Omer?
earlier. So here there's a question, everybody agrees that after the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash they would not eat the new grain until the
seventeenth. Was it based on a תקנה takana or was it based
on a read of the פסוק? pasuk? What is the status when
there is no עומר? Omer Is it חדש permissible from the beginning
of the day or the end of the day? Okay, now it
ends up מפני מה הרחוקים מותרים מחצות היום ולהלן? mipnei mah harichokim
mutarim mechatzot hayom u'lehallan? Now, why when there was an עומר Omer,
could you eat it from midday on? מפני שיודעים שאין בית דין
מתעצלים בו, mipnei she'yod'im she'ein Beis Din mitatzlim bo, they knew that
בית דין Beis Din would not be lazy or negligent, that they
would make sure it would be brought by midday. So when there
is an עומר, Omer it's the עומר Omer, makes it permissible. When
there isn't an עומר, Omer it seems to be a debate in
the משנה: Mishna. does it become biblically permissible
from the beginning
of the day or the end of the day? And that's the
very first thing the גמרא Gemara turns to. Let's take a look.
Rav and Shmuel דאמרי תרוייהו, damri tarvaiyu, Rav and Shmuel both say,
בזמן שבית המקדש קיים, bizman she-Beis HaMikdash kayam, when there's a בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, עומר מתיר. Omer matir. The bringing of the עומר
Omer, makes the new grain permissible. בזמן שאין בית המקדש קיים, bizman
she-ein Beis HaMikdash kayam, when there is no בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
האיר מזרח מתיר, he'ir mizrach matir,
the lighting of the east, meaning when the sun rises in the
east, right, that's when it becomes permissible, as soon as the day
begins, עד עצם היום הזה, ad etzem hayom hazeh, until the day,
as soon as the day begins it becomes permissible.
Okay. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why is that? תרי קראי, trei krah,
there are two verses. It says, כתיב עד הביאכם, ksiv ad havi'achem,
it's forbidden until you bring the עומר, Omer? וכתיב עד עצם היום
הזה, v'ksiv ad etzem hayom hazeh, forbidden until this day. הא כיצד?
ha keitzad? So which is it? Is it until the day or
until the עומר? Omer. כאן בזמן שבית המקדש קיים כאן בזמן שאין
בית המקדש קיים. kan bizman she-Beis HaMikdash kayam kan bizman she-ein Beis
HaMikdash kayam. When there is a בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it's only
when you bring the עומר. Omer, When there's not a בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, it is until the day begins. Now of course it
raises interesting questions. Let's say there is a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
and you forgot to bring it that, you know, you just somehow
didn't bring it. Is it, does it remain forbidden? Did you bring
it late? At that point then retroactively would we say it would
be good from the beginning of the day? That they don't spell
out, but they do say when there's a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
it's about the עומר, Omer not בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash it's about
the beginning of the day. That's what Rav and Shmuel say. Rabbi
Yochanan and Reish Lakish דאמרי תרוייהו, damri tarvaiyu, Rabbi Yochanan and Reish
Lakish say no. אפילו בזמן שבית המקדש קיים, afilu bizman she-Beis HaMikdash
kayam, even when there's a בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, האיר מזרח מתיר,
he'ir mizrach matir, when the,
when it becomes light in the east it becomes permissible, the beginning
of the day. Now you understand that makes a certain amount of
sense because if they're going to say when there's no בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash it's permissible at the beginning of the day, it's hard
to imagine that the presence of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash makes
it more of a problem, makes you have to delay it more.
You know, so, you, so they are saying if we're going to
have to say when there's no בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash it's permissible
at the beginning, even when there is we're going to have to
say it's permissible at the beginning. That it makes it superfluous ביומי,
b'yomei, which is what the גמרא is going to ask. The Beth
position actually is Rabbi Yehuda's. Is when there's no בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash it's the end of the day, and when there is a
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash it's the, it's when the עומר Omer is
brought. That means that the bringing of the עומר Omer is more
effective than the not bringing of the עומר Omer and there not
being a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So that's Rabbi Yehuda in the
משנה. Mishna. That's the Beth. But if you're going to say it's
the beginning of the day then it's, yeah, it's a little strange
to say that it's worse almost with a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
Yeah, this is, funny, these are all מצד סברא, mi-tzad sevara, is
that just because we need to have, I mean, we can't have
grain forbidden for always. A, and B because of the פסוקים, psukim,
there is פסוקים psukim that we can rely on that say עד
עצם היום הזה. ad etzem hayom hazeh. You know, it, if it
were just that מצד סברא mi-tzad sevara we couldn't have the grain
always forbidden, you might have found a way to say when there's
no בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash there's no איסור חדש, issur chadash, which
would have made life a lot easier, but right, but it's also
based on the פסוק. pasuk. What, it still makes, it still doesn't
give a big role for the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Right. According
to, except maybe according to Rav and Shmuel, who say that when
there's no בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash you need the עומר Omer. to
be brought. They don't spell out what would be if you didn't
bring it, but right, Rav and Shmuel have the importance of the
עומר. Omer עד עצם
היום, ad etzem hayom, until the very essence of this day, וקסבר
עד ועד בכלל. v'kasavar ad v'ad b'chlal. So
until the way we've been saying it, which means until the day
begins, here he's reading עד ad means until the end of the
day, right, until and including the day, so therefore it is going
to be prohibited till the end of
the day. The essence, what's, that's what I'm trying to understand. The
essence of this day. But how do you define essence? Midday, when
it's like day is strong, the beginning of the day, until it's
over, until it's passed? Okay, it could mean midday, that we're not
saying. Okay, we're either saying until it begins or until it's over.
Okay. So now what we said is that here's why. You're right.
According, if it's only a מצוה, mitzvah, there would not be a
good reason for Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai to say it. The reason
he is saying it though is because he doesn't, it's not a
תקנה, takkana, he really holds that biblically it's not permitted until the
next day. It doesn't sound that way in the משנה. Mishna, It
sounds like he's arguing on Rabbi Yehuda, but that's what we are
saying here. So now the גמרא continues, let's take a look. ומי
סבר לה כוותיה, u-mi savar lah kavaseih, does he really agree with
Rabbi Yehuda? והא מיפלג פליג, v'ha miflag palig, doesn't he argue on
him? דתנן, de-tnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishna משחרב בית המקדש
התקין רבן יוחנן בן זכאי שיהא יום הנף כולו אסור, mishecharav Beis
HaMikdash hiskin Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai she-yehei yom haneif kulo asur, that
after the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was destroyed he made a תקנה
takkana that it should be forbidden, and then אמר רבי יהודה, amar
Rabbi Yehuda, Rabbi Yehuda in the משנה Mishna, says, הלא מן התורה
הוא אסור, halo min ha-Torah hu asur, how could you say it's
a תקנה? takkana? Biblically it's forbidden until the end of the day,
דכתיב עד עצם היום הזה, de-ksiv ad etzem hayom hazeh, until this
very day. Say the גמרא says, רבי יהודה הוא דקא טעי, Rabbi
Yehuda hu de-katai, Rabbi Yehuda misunderstood Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai. הוא סבר,
hu savar, he thought Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai מדרבנן קאמר, mi-derabbanan ka-amar,
he thought Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai was saying rabbinically you have to
wait until the next day. דלא היא, de-la hi, that's not true,
מדאורייתא קאמר, mi-de'oraisa ka-amar, he was really saying biblically, he was saying
exactly what Rabbi Yehuda said, that biblically you have to wait till
the day is over. So the גמרא says, והא התקין קתני, v'ha
hiskin ktani, but it says that he made a תקנה, takkana, which
is a classic verb for a rabbinic institution. מאי התקין? mai hiskin?
No, what does it mean he made a תקנה? takkana? דרש והתקין.
darash v'hiskin. It means he expounded and established the practice. It was
a biblical issue, people weren't aware of it. Until now there had
been a בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, nobody knew what to do without
a בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, so he made it clear. that without
a בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash you can go ahead, this is the
הלכה, halacha, you have to wait until the next day and it's
not a rabbinic institution. Okay, I can see pre-בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
as a source for what could have taken place at
the במות. bamos. Oh, that's a good question. Why we never look
at the במות bamos question. Well, they would still bring the עומר
Omer when there was a במה גדולה. bama gedola. The במה גדולה.
bama gedola. The question is what would they do when there was
not even a במה גדולה? bama gedola? Yeah, I don't know. Good
question. Okay, I mean the גמרא does discuss that in קידושין, Kiddushin,
I think, when it discusses as soon as they entered into ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. I'd have to look. Okay, so now what do
we have? We have the following. We have and this now is
going to get very practical, the next few lines. So we have
the following, that רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel
with a בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, obviously the עומר Omer is מתיר.
matir. Without a בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you have ר' יהודה Rebbe
Yehuda that says it's at the end of the day. You have
implicitly ר' יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan until we've reread ר' יוחנן, Rebbe Yochanan,
but everybody else, רב ושמואל, Rav u'Shmuel, ר' יוחנן וריש לקיש, Rebbe
Yochanan v'Reish Lakish, whatever, ר' יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan says the beginning of
the day biblically, rabbinically you wait until the end of the day.
And then we had this interesting question, when there was a בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, would the beginning of the day do anything? And
according to ר' יוחנן וריש לקיש, Rebbe Yochanan v'Reish Lakish, it technically
would be permitted from the beginning of the day, which really, as
רש"י Rashi says, as the גמרא says, downplays the role of the
עומר Omer according to that approach. Okay, so now we're going to
look at how we פוסקן, pasken, which is both a question of
how we פוסקן pasken in the debate of the משנה, but also
about how we פוסקן pasken regarding חדש בחוץ לארץ. chadash be'chutz la'aretz.
So these next two lines are very important for הלכה למעשה. halacha
l'maaseh. So let's take a look. Okay,
רב פפא ורב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Rav Pappa v'Rav Huna brei
d'Rav Yehoshua, רב פפא Rav Pappa and רב הונא Rav Huna the
son of רב יהושע, Rav Yehoshua, they obviously were in חוץ לארץ
chutz la'aretz and after the destruction of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
אכלו חדש באורתא דשיתסר נגהי שיבסר. Achlu chadash be'orta d'shitsar nogei shivsar.
They ate חדש on the night of the sixteenth before the seventeenth.
Okay, meaning, meaning that they ate it basically מוצאי motzei the sixteenth.
They forbidden the whole sixteenth, they waited until the seventeenth. Now if
you read it, that's okay, that's ר' יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan and ר'
יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, they waited the whole sixteenth. No, but there's an
issue. If they're in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, what other thing do
they have to contend with in terms of days? Right, יום טוב
שני, Yom Tov Sheni, ספקא דיומא. sfeika d'yoma.
So if we're going to play the whole ספקא דיומא sfeika d'yoma
game, so now we should not only say that the sixteenth is
forbidden, we should even say that the seventeenth is forbidden, but they
actually began eating on the seventeenth, the night of the sixteenth leading
into the seventeenth. How did they do that? What about ספקא דיומא?
sfeika d'yoma? So let's see what it says. קסברי, Ksavri, they were
of the opinion, that חדש בחוץ לארץ דרבנן. chadash be'chutz la'aretz de'rabbanan.
Now that's a very important line for הלכה. halacha. חדש in חוץ
לארץ chutz la'aretz is only a rabbinic issue. ולספיקא לא חיישינן, U'lesfeika
lo chaishinan, so we don't play the whole ספקא דיומא sfeika d'yoma
game together with the prohibition of חדש בחוץ לארץ. chadash be'chutz la'aretz.
חדש בחוץ לארץ Chadash be'chutz la'aretz itself is only rabbinic. We're not
going to pile onto that rabbinic thing to say ספקא דיומא sfeika
d'yoma and pretend that today might be the fifteenth and not the
sixteenth. So we'll be able to go מעיקר הדין me'ikar hadin and
start eating at the seventeenth and not wait until the eighteenth. Wouldn't
you be able to apply onto this the איסור מלאכה issur melacha
of יום טוב, Yom Tov, so that maybe they don't necessarily need
the end of the day, they're just waiting because they can't reap
the grain? Or harvest the grain. Right, this הלכה halacha and really
they even hold it until the next day. Well, no, that might
be, but the גמרא isn't going there. Anyway, yeah, you're really kind
of divorcing the whole the during בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash way it
works from the post-בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash time, because the idea that
the second day, like יום טוב שני Yom Tov Sheni in חוץ
לארץ, chutz la'aretz, would have any bearing on this when it really
depends on something that occurs in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Yes,
but the whole point of חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz is because we
are acting as if we don't know what day it really is
and when it really did happen in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
So if today really was not the sixteenth but the fifteenth and
they wouldn't have brought the עומר Omer today, they were only going
to bring the עומר Omer. tomorrow, da-da-da-da-da, right? Right, in חוץ לארץ
בזמן בית המקדש, chutz la'aretz bizman Beis Hamikdash, they still would have
had ספקא דיומא שאלה. sfeika d'yoma shayla. Yes. And they would have
waited until midday. Right, the next day. Right, but they wouldn't have
waited the whole day because there would have been an עומר. Yes,
Rachel. About what you said on שבת Shabbos that in this particular
instance there is not really ספקא דיומא sfeika d'yoma because it's oh,
well that's also true. In שבועות Shavuos there's never ספקא דיומא. sfeika
d'yoma. You know, that's an excellent point that I had forgotten that,
but that's true. In שבועות Shavuos no, but this wasn't שבועות Shavuos
yet. This was פסח. This was the beginning of the process. So
פסח there would be ספקא דיומא. sfeika d'yoma. That was the one
יום טוב Yom Tov they really did have ספקא דיומא. sfeika d'yoma.
Right. Okay, so anyway,
let's just finish let's just finish looking at the whole range of
opinions. So that's number one. It was חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. They
should have waited if they would have applied ספקא דיומא sfeika d'yoma
until eighteen, but they waited until seventeen because they held that חדש
בחוץ לארץ chadash be'chutz la'aretz was only rabbinic anyway. רבנן דבי רב
אשי, Rabbanan d'bei Rav Ashi, however, the rabbis of רב אשי'ס Rav
Ashi's ישיבה, yeshiva, אכלו בצפרא דשיבסר. Achlu betzafra d'shivsar. They did not
eat the night leading into the seventeenth, they waited until the morning
of the seventeenth. What's the logic there? קסברי חדש בחוץ לארץ דאורייתא.
Ksavri chadash be'chutz la'aretz de'oraisa. They held that it's biblical. Okay, if
it's biblical then you should be waiting and you want to do
ספקא דיומא, sfeika d'yoma, you should be waiting until the eighteenth. What
are they doing eating in the morning of the seventeenth?